And for Tesla and AI Native DevCon, the
organization here has been just amazing.
I'm Ray Meyers. Welcome to AI hates
legacy code. Now, people sometimes ask
for my slides. You can find them at
raymyers.org/talks.
I currently work at OpenHands, the
leading open source coding agent, which
as of yesterday is officially a series A
startup as well. I've also worked at
some places you've heard of. Uh coding
agents are cool. We all can agree on
that.
What isn't cool is
if one deletes someone's production
database
despite explicit instructions not to. I
don't consider that cool. has happened
to someone a few months ago, you may
have heard, or when, for instance, it
edits your make file to make the test
report passing even when they've failed
as happened to me while I was preparing
this talk.
This is a true story. Now, um these
quirky behaviors relate to, you know,
model behaviors that we've given names
like reward tampering and
hallucinations. These are things that
the leading model labs like Enthropic
have been trying to stamp out for well
over a year. Uh but despite their
efforts and some progress, this is still
like a very regular part of your
experience. If you're using coding
agents downstream of the models and if
you're an agent builder like myself,
these represent
bugs we can't fix. We have no path to
fixing these bugs under our present
assumptions.
So, do we need to change those
assumptions is the question I'm raising.
And people have different ideas about
that. It depends on what your needs are,
honestly. Perhaps you're from the land
of demos, [snorts] the land of
prototypes. You're from the land of new
code, some of you, and therefore you are
from the land where above all AI works.
You may not have a problem.
You're from a place I like to call pitch
deck paradise. I've I've tried to draw a
representation of it. It's a strange
place to me. I imagine it as fields of
green because you do green field
development. There's a pot of gold
there. I know that's very important.
Maybe you've got like a magic mushroom.
I don't know your life. I'm from a
different place. I'm at a startup now
and it's not my first, but I am from
Legacy Mountain.
When people are from different places,
it's sometimes hard for them to
communicate with one another. And so I
like to wrestle with the dialogue that
I've been seeing over the past year or
so.
People from pitch paradise will say that
AI coding is a gamecher and they are
reporting their true lived experience.
They are right.
Whereas people from Legacy Mountain will
hear that and say your AI doesn't work
and they are also right. They are
reporting their true lived experience.
But people from pitch paradise don't
understand how someone's experiences
could be so much different from theirs.
They say, "You must be close-minded.
This must be the issue." And start
blaming the users. But it still is a
thing that doesn't work in their world.
This does nothing to help the situation.
And then they will try and threaten us.
And they will say, "You will be left
behind." I have seen hundreds of people
say, "You're going to be left behind."
as though I'm in the freaking rapture
or in a a bem movie franchise starring
Kurt Cameron instead of trying to have a
nuance technical discussion.
Threatening also doesn't make it work.
It it just doesn't work. We're
reporting.
What will help is if the dialogue
becomes let's fix it. And that's the
dialogue I want to have. So I declare a
truce. There have been some harsh words
on both sides, I'm sure. heart emoji,
handshake, whatever you need on behalf
of Legacy Mountain. I welcome you
because you are trying to climb Legacy
Mountain and I respect that. We need all
the help we can get.
There is some disagreement about how far
up it we are. For instance, we have
these great benchmarks like Swebench,
which is um representative of real tasks
that had to be done on real GitHub
repositories. And I think there's strong
consensus the fact that we have many
agents now exceeding 70% at what's
called the verified subset. These kinds
of benchmark results represent real
economic value. These are not vanity
metrics. But how does this translate?
How far up the mountain are we? Does 70%
Swedbench mean we're 70% up legacy
mountain? Some people talk as though
that's the case. It will get you some
some shares on LinkedIn, I'm sure. Um,
others, and I'm closer to this view,
feel like this is actually 70% up
something pretty interesting, but it's
so far down the bottom that you can't
even see the top from where we are.
So, Legacy Mountain, we'll find is a
treacherous place. Sometimes it could
feel more like this mountain.
And you may not want to look at that.
You may not want to think about that. I
don't blame you. One does not simply
walk into Mordor, but we have no choice.
The core the code was forged in the
fires of Mount Doom and only there can
it be unmade.
And just like Gandalf said, I am not
trying to rob you. I am trying to help
you when I say AI hates legacy code.
So this would be a good time to define
terms. What could I mean by this in this
context? What I mean is systems based on
large language models are illequipped
for the challenges of existing
production code. [clears throat]
AI of course can mean many other things.
They don't literally hate anything. But
in this context I'm talking time that
the current assumptions building coding
agents this is this is what I I mean the
challenge is
now I've said legacy code is any
existing code in production your
business depends on
there are particular pieces of legacy
code that are usually referred to in
this way because they they are
challenging and so when we talk about
the legacy code challenge is usually
some combination of it being old or
archaic done in an old way we wouldn't
do now brittle it breaks easily. It's
untested. It's forgotten. We We're
missing some context. Some people have
moved on.
But all this boils down to we fear to
change it. If on pitch deck paradise you
believe we're afraid to adopt AI, you're
partly right. There is fear. But it's
actually a sadder situation than us
being afraid of the new technology.
We're afraid of the old technology.
We're afraid of our own systems. In
software engineering, the reality in the
industry is we are quite literally
afraid of our own legacy. That's what
you're walking into. Good luck. I'll try
and help you. Now, why is this a problem
for large language models specifically?
You've probably heard throughout 2023
that it is easy to get large language
models to give you good value when the
tasks have certain properties. Like for
instance, I can ask chat GBT to give me
a silly goose. I get a silly goose.
Okay, very good. But more generally,
tend to excel when it's low risk, there
is a clear context, and it is easy to
check the result. I looked at it, it's
clearly a silly goose. Okay, fine.
Actually, there's some dispute on this.
Uh, Opus has claimed it's actually a
duck. We'll look into that with an aven
pathologist and get back to you. So
regardless in Legacy Mountain, it is
often the case that the exact opposite
is true. It is a high-risk task because
you're by definition working on
something your business depends on.
There is an unclear context and the
result is not easy to check. So LLMs
fail or if they don't, they require
these elaborate workarounds to manage
the risk.
So we see our experience is so different
because we have different needs and what
we don't need I claim are excuses. I
have been hearing some excuses
not to point any fingers in the in the
direction unnecessarily of of of any
particular people in pitch paradise but
these things are in the air. One the
models will get better. This well true I
claim is an excuse because the models
don't get better in every conceivable
way imaginable equally which is I think
what this is a placeholder to mean. We
have seen very clearly they get better
in some dimensions and not in others. If
you're going to make a statement like
the models will get better I would say
maybe specify what behavior you'll think
they'll get better at and how will you
know when they're there. I think this
has become too big of a panacea to wait
for. Another thing that said is humans
mistake make mistakes too. Again,
technically true and somewhat useless.
This is a thought-terminating cliche.
Humans do make mistakes and we have to
deal with the consequences of that. And
LM are not people. They make different
mistakes for different reasons. So if
you're using this at the beginning of a
statement and saying and then how do we
problem solve from there? Fine, not an
excuse, but don't use it at the end of
thought. That'd be a thought terminating
cliche. Then we have blaming the user.
Now, we're going to establish these
tools are very confusing to get real
results on in many realistic con
context. So, if you blame the user for
not knowing your your latest 20 tips,
trips, tricks, and techniques, you're
ultimately just holding back your
product from getting better. Empathy for
the users will produce innovation that
gives us better experiences.
So, we're done with the excuses. Let's
talk about getting better. There's two
people we could be talking to, two two
groups, though they do uh strongly
overlap.
A user of coding agents, if you're not
interested in building and improving the
the agents we've got, but you want to do
better using, I do have some some words
for you, but also we're going to talk
about getting better as tool builders.
As a user, I would say apply software
craft. You can learn how to use AI.
That's great. I'd like you to do that.
But there is still something happening
here that is kind of just the physics of
the situation you're on. You can call it
software craft or software engineering.
And we've had it for a long time. Most
of it's still relevant. And most
importantly, we know how to teach it. So
you have a clearer path to learning
that. When I say apply software craft
some starting points, these are some
books that I I would highly recommend.
Working effectively with legacy code,
Michael Feathers. Kill it with fire,
Marian Botti. Modern software
engineering by Dave Farley. These are
some people with blogs and videos I find
very useful as well. If you've got some
legacy code challenge, people like this
have probably said something very
helpful to you that you could go and
seek out and then you'll be able to
apply that insight to use your AI better
as well if that's what you're doing. Are
there resources for craft plus AI? Well,
we're not quite so far along where we
understand how to teach it even and the
base knowledge is is changing so
quickly. But I would like to call out
some work. A lot of Kessler gave a a
fantastic master class yesterday
morning. Uh she's here in the front row.
So so so thank you for this. and she has
an amazing GitHub repository that that
she and others including the Simon
Technical Coaching Society have
contributed to where they're gathering
here's what we have have learned to do
to use coding agents in a way that's
very principled with what we know about
software engineering as well. This is a
sampling of her talk from yesterday.
This is just a map of just the things
she was able to cover in in the first
two hours you know with the master
class. um it's just scratching the
surface of the workarounds they've
cataloged. This should tell us something
about the tools. We could start taking
lessons from this so that people have to
memorize fewer workarounds very clearly.
So these coding agent skills they often
have to do with managing context,
managing the risk either using these
software craft skills or by reducing the
task size things like this or they're
customizing how you're using the agents.
Your agents all have some amount of
customizability. You should learn how to
use that. Something we've just announced
in uh open hands version one is we've
extracted out the core agent that makes
the the box tick into something called
the software agent SDK. So this will
allow you to start scripting uh how
you're using the agent with uh actual
code. You're not limited to only
prompting. I think this is very
important for reasons I I hope will
become uh clear, but generally speaking,
learn to customize the tools you're
using because they're they're really not
a complete experience for the full range
of tasks you're going to see. Getting
better as a tool builder then is help
your users, which I hope would be
obvious. Help them to apply software
craft, which is the goal. Also, help
them understand your tool with clear
predictable behaviors that they can
learn and that they can trust.
Currently, our tools are a little bit
too much like a magic box. On Legacy
Mountain, we don't need a magic box. We
need a wrench. I know what it does, and
it fits in my hand.
So, how do we do that? Let's go back to
this central challenge. I'm arguing
we're facing that solutions based on
large language models are illquipped for
the challenges of existing production
code. If we take that as not just a
defeist slogan but it is some
non-mporary state of affairs to contend
with. It does suggest solutions right
perhaps our solutions should not be
based so much on large language models.
Perhaps we should just reduce our
dependence a little bit. Let's talk
about what that means.
like to simplify the domain of
components we can use into two axes.
Scope, how general they are, and
confidence, how confident we are in what
they're doing. Language models, the the
big ones, the frontier, the foundation
models, if you like, they are very high
in the scope of what they can attempt to
do. That is super interesting. It's
understandable. We're excited about
that. algorithms on the other hand as
well as the old school symbolic AI they
are we're highly confident in what they
are doing um within the tiny scope that
they've been designed for and so if
you're trying to reach that upper right
corner where you have a wide scope and
high confidence then you can try to take
LLMs and push higher confidence or you
can take algorithms and try to level up
in scope um and lot of excitement
lot of money in this angle, right? Try
to try to push it all through LLM by
improving the LLM raises all boats. Uh
but as engineers,
we're not limited. We can do both. We
can use these both together in in kind
of infinite combinations. So, um that's
that's the shape of things, you know, in
in a nutshell. Here are some examples of
that. Again, what we're trying to do is
give these tools clear, predictable
behaviors that people can learn and
understand and trust, allow our users to
form a mental model. My first time
addressing AI native dev, I came to New
York February and I gave this talk make
tools that don't break uh about working
with some code like this and worse using
refactoring algorithms. There's another
um talk that's coming on right after
mine by the CEO of Open Hands, Robert,
and it's called Managing Fleets of
Coding Agents with Open Hands. I'll I'll
mention a taste of what's in that, but
it talks about our um approach so far on
these long horizon tasks, we say, these
these larger code bases that present
these problems. Another one I'd like to
call out that's also right after mine,
so watch one in online and one in
person, I guess, is DevOps agents that
can't delete your database by my friend
George from Stackpack. We, you know, I
love that premise. So,
um, the first one of of mine I just
mentioned, that's refactoring code
safely by algorithm, not seeing humans
or LLMs as the things that should
directly be editing the code. the uh
Roberts is uh involves breaking down
tasks by studying the source code and
making this dependency graph before we
give tasks to to agents this fleet of
agents and uh George's is about using a
policy engine to enforce what uh what
the agent does or at least that's the
part of the technology I'm highlighting.
So if we combine those first two ideas
as sometimes we do in in some of these
openends migrations we're looking at
then we've got static analysis of the
source code making this dependency tree
and coming up with then how are we going
to partition out and order these tasks
so that we can address them with agents
in parallel but they're set up so they
don't crash into each other. They have
uh responsibilities where they're
unlikely to kind of overlap. Right? So
we're setting the task up for success.
Then we have our little our little
worker bees, the fleet of agents doing
what they do. But then on the end when
we're uh editing the code where
possible, we can still do that with
syntax transforms just through agent
tool use tools like like as GP, Java
parser, and others. So interesting thing
there. This is like turning a compiler
inside out. There's a there's an LLM
based agent, but the rest of what's
going on looks like the inside of a
compiler. That's because compilers are
really good at thinking about code and
LLMs, it turns out, are not compilers.
That's my opinion. Maybe that's the next
talk. Um, you give me a time check here.
I'll break down
>> We good?
>> Perfect. So, I I'd like to then break
down a little bit of some of what makes
uh George's engine tick. And I think
this will be a little deeper up the
stack than the things he's going to
cover in in his talk. But stackback is a
DevOps flavored coding agent. It has a
lot of domain specific stuff they're
targeting for uh for operations uh
domains and it has internally a
permission system called Warden that
uses Cedar policies. Cedar is a
technology made by Amazon for enforcing
uh policies in this domain specific
language. An interesting thing about
Cedar is Cedar is formally verified u
meaning there are aspects that are
mathematically proven which I will show
you.
Um to my knowledge this is the first use
of formal verification in a coding agent
product and there are many research
examples. I think this is the first
example that that went all the way to
production. Let me know if I've missed
one because I'm cataloging them in a
little repo called awesome verified
coding agents and to kind of track these
these emerging efforts because I just I
just want to highlight this really
advanced use of algorithms together with
LLMs to you know deliver these these
high assurance experiences. What does
this look like up in uh Amazon's Cedar,
right? It's um an open source library
that parses this DSL domain specific
language about what people are allowed
to access what resources and so on. Um,
so we've got a forbid there and a permit
there. And then there's code in that
engine written in Rust, right? So we say
we authorize things and it's executing a
particular bit of logic there like if
something is marked both that it should
be forbidden and that it should be
permitted then forbidden should win.
Right? This is a a log piece of logic
they'd call forbid trumps permit. And
it's very important to them that that
code does what we've just said. If it
didn't, it would be a big problem. Um,
so they want to make extra sure not just
for the inputs we're going to test on,
but actually for every conceivable input
we could have. There are ways of doing
that. The way they've done it here is
they've implemented a reference
implementation of that Cedar engine
that's in Rust. They've got a parallel
implementation that's in a language
called lean which you can do
mathematical proofs on. Field metalist
mathematicians use it to to verify their
results these days. So they've got you
know a slightly translated kind of
purely functional version of that is
authorized method. And then because it's
in lean they have a theorem about that.
And there are almost 2,000 such theorems
in the Cedar Spec codebase
where that top part is basically code as
you'd understand it just knowing that
the uh arrow is an implies arrow. If you
were to look at it for longer than I'll
have it up, you'd understand. But the
rest of it is something that might be
new to some of you which is called a
proof script. It's a series of tactics
that are used to prove that statement.
This is just one step of that. I won't
walk you through the whole proof right
now, but this is this is a short
understandable one. When you use this in
an interactive theorem prover, which is
what I spent a lot of the last year um
studying,
there's this thing on the right hand
side called a proof state. And you look
at the current state of the goal at the
bottom you're trying to prove. You'll
notice it has that is authorized
function referenced. So there's going to
be a tactic executed here. Someone has
looked at that and said, "Ah, what I
need to do is inline is authorized." I
need to start explode the definition of
that into my proof state. using it's
called unfold in the language of these
theorem tactics and then I have the
definition of it there and I can start
doing further steps manipulating it and
simplifying it so that I've proven the
end result. So this is like tests but
can prove things for all possible inputs
not just the inputs and the tests. So
how many of you have seen a tactic
prover before an interactive theorem
prover like that? Okay, at least one
person. So if the rest of you haven't,
now you have. And there are endless
possibilities. The entirety of computer
science, past, present, and future, is
at our disposal. The one thing we can't
do is escape old code. Even if we
escaped all the code that's old today,
new code becomes old.
So
I hope as we climb legacy mountain, we
can at least agree on this. Whatever
techniques and magic and models and
chicainery we use, let us work together
to make legacy a word we can speak with
pride instead of fear.
Let that be our legacy. Thank you.
[music]
>> [music]